Finding Aid for Migrant Health Promotion records, 1982-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Migrant Health Promotion records 1982-2012
Migrant Health Promotion (Organization)
93812 Bf 2
Organization established to improve the health and living conditions of migrant farmworkers in six states of the Upper Midwest. Administrative records; program files detailing operation of Camp Health Aide program and publication of Migrant Health Service Directory; topical files, and videotapes publicizing camp health aide program.
13.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of the organization (donor no. 8118 ) and came to the library through the organization's executive director. Numerous additional materials have been received.
The record group is open to research.
The Migrant Health Promotion (formerly known as the Midwest Migrant Health Information Office, or MMHIO) was established in 1983 as an initiative of the National Migrant Worker Council, Inc. Its aim was to improve the health and living conditions of migrant farmworkers in a six state area encompassing the upper Midwest. All of the programs of the Migrant Health Promotion are directed toward reducing the cultural, language, and transportation barriers preventing migrant farmworkers from having access to health care services, and beyond that, to increasing the participation of migrant families in their own health care.
The Migrant Health Promotion works in collaboration with Catholic health providers in the Midwest collectively known as the Catholic Consortium for Migrant Health. On its own, the Migrant Health Promotion has designed two projects intended to lower the barriers to good health care. These are the Camp Health Aide Program and the Migrant Health Services Directory. Begun in 1985, the Camp Health Aide Program trains aides among the migrants in the basics of health care. These aides are then a link between the migrants and the health care professionals in the various camp areas. Funding for the camp aide program comes from the Catholic Consortium and the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. Since its inception, the Camp Health Aide Program has become the main focus of the Migrant Health Promotion, expanding to cover migrants' home states as well as the Midwest. The Migrant Health Services Directory describes migrant health services in federally funded clinics throughout the upper Midwest. The directory is then distributed to migrants and migrant service agencies, schools, churches, and health clinics throughout the Midwest and the migrant home bases in Texas and Florida. Through these programs, the Migrant Health Promotion has become a leader in migrant health care, providing assistance to other agencies trying to implement lay health programs. In the 1990s the Migrant Health Promotion developed a number of adaptations of the original Camp Health Aide Program model to build on community strengths and meet complex health needs. The Infórmate Teen Health Program began in Manchester, Michigan in 1995 and offered peer health education and group activities led by Teen Health Aides. Since its inception, Infórmate has expanded to various sites throughout Michigan and South Texas, and added a traveling Teen Theater Troupe. In 1998 the organization changed its name from the Midwest Migrant Health Information Office to the Migrant Health Promotion in order to reflect the organization's growing activities outside the Midwest.
The Migrant Health Promotion records document the efforts of one organization to provide health care assistance to the migrant workers of the Midwest. Beyond the history of the organization itself, the records detail something of the life and condition of workers in the migrant camps during the 1980s and 1990s with special emphasis on their health care needs.
The records of the Migrant Health Promotion have been arranged into eight series: Administrative Records; Outreach; Camp Aide Program (CHAP); Other Programs and Related Materials; Topical Files; Photographs; Videotapes; and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Mexican Americans--Health and hygiene.; Midwest Migrant Health Information Office.; Migrant agricultural laborers.; Migrant Health Promotion (Organization); Migrant labor.; Migrant labor--Medical care.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Mexican Americans--Health and hygiene.; Midwest Migrant Health Information Office.; Migrant agricultural laborers.; Migrant Health Promotion (Organization); Migrant laborers.; Sparta (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Color slides.; DVDs.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records document the beginnings of the Migrant Health Promotion and the formation of its various programs. It has been divided into three subseries, records from 1982-1989, 1990-1996, and records after 1997. The largest and most substantive portion of the first subseries is a set of "Administrative and Policy Notebooks." These are of two sorts: (1) three volumes cover the years 1983-1984 and include the MMHIO statement of purpose and philosophy, study of the migrant "stream" north and maps listing location of migrant health care facilities, and notes of MMHIO personnel who visited the various camps; (2) 4 volumes probably intended as the executive director's ready reference files and consisting of quarterly reports, financial reports, grant proposals, and related information. Another significant set of materials is a set of volumes labeled "Grant Proposals" and consisting of the various proposals made by MMHIO to state and federal agencies to fund its program of migrant health services directories and more especially its program of migrant camp health aides. The later subseries also contains grants proposals, as well as other fundraising strategies and the organization's strategic planning materials.
  - 1982-1989
    - Annual Reports/Background materials (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Migrant Health Needs Assessment, Midwest Stream February 1984 (Box 1)
    - Study circa 1984 "Analysis of Parameters Affecting Services to Migrants" (Box 1)
    - Administrative and Policy Notebooks
      - Notebook 1983 containing purpose and philosophy of MMHIO and the National Migrant Worker Council, study of migration patterns, and state maps showing migrant health project administrative offices and sites of migrant health clinics (Box 1)
      - Notebook 1983-1984 containing policy manual, "anecdotal notes" about various migrant health clinic sites, and site visit analysis forms (Box 1)
      - Notebook 1983-1984 containing site visit and phone interviews with information about the various health clinic services available to migrants, "anecdotal notes," and itineraries of visits to various camp sites (Box 1)
      - Notebooks containing quarterly reports, financial reports, grant proposals, and National Migrant Worker Council materials
        - 1983-1986 (Box 1)
        - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
        - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
        - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Grant Proposals
      - 1982/1983-1985/86 (Box 3)
      - 1986 Michigan Expansion Proposal (Box 3)
      - 1986-1987 (State) (Box 3)
      - 1986-1987 (Federal) (Box 3)
      - 1987-1988 (Federal) (Box 3)
      - 1987/1988-1988/1989 (State) (Box 3)
      - 1989-1990 (Federal) (Box 3)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - 1990-1996
    - Annual Report 1992 (Box 14)
    - Board Development undated (Box 3)
    - Fundraising
      - Board of Directors Letter Campaign 1996 (Box 3)
      - Funding Promotion for Wisconsin CHAP 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - Funding Strategy 1991-1994 (Box 3)
      - Health Education Training Center Alliance of Texas (Box 3)
      - Rural Health Outreach Funds 1991 (Box 3)
    - Grant Proposal 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Job Descriptions undated (Box 3)
    - Marketing Workshop 1995 (Box 3)
    - Midwest Migrant Health Information Office Incorporation 1992 (Box 3)
    - National Advisory Council on Migrant Health Award 1995 (Box 3)
    - Program Coordinators' meeting, Florida 1994 (Box 3)
    - Proposals
      - Americorps 1994-1996 (Box 3)
      - Diabetes Video Project with University of Michigan (Box 3)
      - Fannie Mae Foundation 1994 (Box 3)
      - Federal Grant 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - Healthy Tomorrows for Children 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - Kellogg Foundation (Box 3)
      - Levi Strauss Foundation 1994 (Box 3)
      - Robert Wood Johnson "Opening Doors" 1994 (Box 3)
      - "Travelling Lay Health Advisor Program" Proposal to CDC 1993 (Box 3)
    - Strategic Planning 1992-1995 (Box 3)
    - Technical assistance log 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - 1997-2007
    - Annual Campaign 1997-2001, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Annual Reports 1997-2011 (Box 14)
    - Awards
      - Border Models of Excellence 2002-2004 (Box 3)
      - Models that Work Strategy Transfer Guide 1997 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors 1997, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Brochures (Box 3)
    - Endowment 2002 (Box 3)
    - Executive Director search 2007 (Box 3)
    - Executive Director search 2007 (Box 14)
    - Financial Report 2010 (Box 3)
    - Personnel Policy Manual 1998, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Retreats 2000, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Strategic Planning 1997-2004 (Box 3)
    - Webpage Information 1997-1999 (Box 3)
- Outreach
  The Outreach series consists principally of records of professional conferences, and presentations given mostly by June Grube Robinson, the program director in charge of the Camp Health Aide Program. Topics focus on the benefits of lay health programs, with some workshops on how to implement and maintain similar projects. There is also a small subseries of articles written by Migrant Health Promotion staff, and a small subseries of Migrant Health Promotion research, including studies on migrant living conditions and an outreach survey given to migrant workers.
  - Articles
    - "Changes in Empowerment: Effects of Participation in a Lay Health Promotion Program" 1997 (Box 3)
    - "Effectiveness of Community Health Workers for Promoting Use of Safety Eyewear by Latino Farm Workers," 2004 (Box 3)
    - "Occupational Health Survey of Farm Workers by Camp Health Aides," 2006 (Box 3)
    - "Using Theatrical Presentations as a Means of Disseminating Knowledge of HIV/AIDS Risk Factors to Migrant Farm Workers," 2007 (Box 3)
  - Conferences and Presentations
    - CHAP Occupational Health Survey Presentation at Agricultural Health and Safety Conference 1997 (Box 3)
    - CHAP Presentation to National Advisory Council on Migrant Health 1989 (Box 3)
    - CHAP Workshop at National Farmworker Conference 1993 (Box 3)
    - CHAP Presentation at Maternal/Child Health Leadership Conference 1993 (Box 3)
    - CHAP Presentation, Conference on Health Issues for Women of Color 1997 (Box 3)
    - Community Health and Immigrant Women in MI, MI Women's Studies Association Conference 1997 (Box 3)
    - Farmworker Men as Peer Health Educators Workshop 1994 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising for a CHA Program, Workshop 1992 (Box 3)
    - Geographic Comparison of CHA sites, APHA Conference 1995 (Box 3)
    - Lay Health Advisor Workshop at Migrant Health Conference 1990 (Box 3)
    - Lay Health Worker Program and Policy Development Workshop, APHA Conference 1992 (Box 3)
    - Listening to and Hearing Your Client, Healthy Mothers Healthy Babies Conference 1995 (Box 3)
    - Migrant Health Newsline Article on CHAP, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Nutrition Education through CHAP, presented at National Farmworker Conference 1993 (Box 3)
    - Nutrition Guest Lecture, UofM Nutrition Class 1990 (Box 4)
    - Personal Empowerment in CHA's, APHA Conference 1996 (Box 4)
    - Popular Education Workshop at American Public Health Association Conference 1995 (Box 4)
    - Promoting Healthy Lives 2001 (Box 4)
    - Promotores(as): Access to our Communities Workshop 2004 (Box 4)
    - Support Systems for Women through Lay Health Promotion Programs, U.S.-Mexico Border Conference on Women's Health 1995 (Box 4)
    - Tools for Building Your Promotor(a) Program (CD-R) (Box 4)
  - Research
    - Farmworker Occupational Health Surveillance 1995-1998 (Box 4)
    - Migrant Health Needs Assessment 1984 (Box 4)
    - Migrant Studies 1986-1989 (Box 4)
    - Midwest Migrant Health Information Office Provider Survey 1993 (Box 4)
    - Outreach Survey 1988 (Box 4)
- Camp Health Aide Program (CHAP)
  The Camp Health Aide Program series includes documentation about the development of the program and annual reports, but more valuable is the information given about the individuals who participate in the program. In addition to the manuals and teaching materials given to the migrant health aides, the Migrant Health Promotion records include personnel information about the aides and interviews with them about the problems they face working in the migrant health care clinics. There are also files related to additional programs run as part of Camp Health Aide.
  - Administrative Materials
    - Camp Health Aide contact information and bios 1985-1994 (Box 4)
    - Camp Health Aide Personal data forms (Box 4)
    - Camp Health Aide Daily Logs (sample only) containing services provided to individual patients, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Camp Health Aide Program Forms (Box 4)
    - Contracts and Financial Information 1986-1989 (Box 4)
    - Employment Status and Liability of Camp Health Aides 1988-1993 (Box 4)
    - Evaluation Projects
      - Assessment of Program Performance 1986-1987 (Box 4)
      - Final Reports
        - 1989 (includes photos) (Box 4)
        - Florida 1997-1999 (Box 4)
        - Illinois 1996-1999 (Box 4)
        - Indiana 1988-1989 (Box 4)
        - Michigan
          - 1986-1987 (Box 4)
          - 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 4)
          - Anecdotal information and program objectives 1989 (Box 4)
          - 1990, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
        - Minnesota 1994-1995 (Box 5)
        - Ohio 1987-1992 (Box 5)
        - Wisconsin 1989-1995 (scattered) (Box 5)
      - Effectiveness Evaluation 1989-1995 (Box 5)
      - Evaluation Questionnaires 1992 (Box 5)
      - Evaluation Workshop 1992 (Box 5)
      - Home Based Health Education Final Report 1993-1994 (Box 5)
      - "Preliminary Data Analysis," 1986 (Box 5)
      - Reporting Notebook 2005 (Box 5)
      - Scholarship Evaluation 1995 (Box 5)
      - Temperance Camp Health Aide Program Report 1998 (Box 5)
    - Field notes 1992 (Box 5)
    - Implementation Guide (Box 5)
    - CHAP implementation information 1991 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Expansion Proposal 1987 (Box 5)
    - National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Program (proposed), rough draft 1984 (Box 5)
    - Program description 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Anecdotes 1996-2002 (Box 5)
  - Article that gives an overview of CHAP 1993 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1985-1991, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Downstream Program Reports
    - Final report 1989-1990 (includes photos and slides) (Box 5)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 5)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Florida CHAP
    - CHAP program 1991 (Box 5)
    - CHA interviews 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Journal entries 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Indiana CHA profiles (includes photos) 1989 (Box 5)
  - La Esperanza, CHA Newsletter 1990-1993 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Letter from a former CHA 1992 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Women's CHAP 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - "Models that Work," 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters 1990-2012 (Box 5)
    (scattered years)
  - Ohio CHAP, Community Health Services 1990 (Box 5)
  - Press release 1988 (Box 5)
  - Projects
    - Capacity Building Assistance Program (Box 5)
    - CHA Education with United Migrant Opportunity Services 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - CHA Women's Farmworker Health Program 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - CHAP Pesticide Education Project 2000 (Box 5)
      (?)
    - Colonia Health Workers managed care program 1995-1999 (Box 5)
    - Home-Base Health Education Program 1993-1995 (Box 5)
    - Parish Nurse Project 1991-1994 (Box 5)
    - Photovoice Project -- Season 2000 (Box 5)
    - Promotora Task Force 1996 (Box 5)
    - Promotora or Promotor de Salud 2005, 2008 undated (Box 5)
    - Substance Abuse Prevention Program (Box 5)
  - Promotional Materials 1989-1993 and undated (Box 6)
  - Proposals
    - Belle Glade Outreach 1991 (Box 6)
    - Delmarva Rural Health Outreach 1991 (Box 6)
    - Parrottsville, Tennessee, CHAP 1991 (Box 6)
    - "Protegete (Protect Yourself) Border Prevention Program" (Box 6)
  - Surveys for outreach nurses (Box 6)
  - Teen Health Aides and teen programs
    - 1994-1995 (Box 6)
    - Infórmate Program 1998-2001 (scattered) (Box 6)
    - Responses to Protegete Program for teen participants (Box 6)
  - Tidwell Family Care Center in El Mirage, AZ 1992-1994 (Box 6)
  - Timeline of CHAP, Infórmate and Colonia Health Worker Program from 1985-2000 (Box 6)
  - Training
    - Orientation Planning (Box 6)
    - Local Program Coordinator Orientation 1898-1990, 1993 (Box 6)
    - Wisconsin Program Coordinator Orientation 1992 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Program Coordinator Orientation 1993 (Box 6)
    - Wisconsin CHA Orientation 1993 (Box 6)
    - Final Report 1995 (Box 14)
    - CHA Credentialing 1996 (Box 6)
  - Wisconsin Migrant Health Meeting 1991 (Box 6)
  - Manuals and Reference Materials
    - Camp Health Aide Manuals
      - 1985 (Box 6)
      - "Melba's working copy for the original manual," 1985 (Box 6)
      - "Melba's working manual," 1986 (Box 6)
      - 1987 (Box 6)
      - 1987-1990 (scattered) (Box 6)
      - 1991 (Box 6)
      - Final Version 1997 (Box 6)
      - English Version 1997, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - English and Spanish version 1997, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - Spanish Version 1997, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Teaching Notes/Lessons 1991-1997 (Box 7)
    - Implementation Guide 1991 (Box 7)
    - Lesson Guide 1987 (Box 7)
    - Program volume 1985-1988 containing forms, communications, interviews with aides, profiles of aides, reports, lists, and related easy access information (Box 7)
    - Michigan Department of Health agreement for the Camp Health Aide Program 1990 (Box 7)
    - Notebook containing photocopies of articles relating to migrant health care issues (Box 7)
- Other Programs and Related Materials
  The Other Programs and Related Materials series documents various programs including the Infórmate program, programs run by Migrant Health Promotion, and lay health partner programs. The Migrant Health Promotion subseries provides information about the Migrant Health Service Directory, and contains of copies of the directory and a report evaluating the effectiveness of the directory. This subseries also documents Adult Education Programs run by the Migrant Health Promotion. The other subseries consists of materials from other lay health programs that collaborated with the Migrant Health Promotion on specific projects.
  - Family Health/La Clinica, Wisconsin 1992 (Box 7)
  - Infórmate
    - Articles about 1999-2009 (Box 14)
    - Calendar 1998 (Box 7)
    - Grant Applications and Correspondence 1997-2000 (Box 7)
    - Implementation Guide (Box 7)
    - Implementation Notes (Box 7)
    - Manual (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Reports
      - Annual report 2003 (Box 7)
      - Final reports 1998-1999 (Box 7)
      - Quarterly reports 1997-2002, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Training Curriculum and Toolkit 2000 (Box 7)
  - Migrant Health Promotion Programs
    - Adult Education
      - Teaching Tips and Tools (Box 7)
      - College and High School Assistance 1989 (Box 7)
      - Teaching Low Literates Workshop 1990 (Box 7)
      - Sisters of Mercy Education Program 1993 (Box 7)
    - Booklet on Texas programs 2002 (Box 7)
    - Colonia Health Worker Outreach Program 2000 (Box 7)
    - Familias Fuertes y Saludables 2005 (Box 7)
    - Madres y Niños 1999 (Box 7)
    - Program report to the Board of Directors for 1999-2000, 2007 (Box 7)
    - Migrant Health Services Directory/La Guia
      - Directories 1984-2007, 3 folders; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 8)
        (includes CD-R)
      - Directory Evaluation 1992 (Box 8)
      - Final Report on Evaluation 1987 (Box 8)
      - History of Discontinuation 2002-2006 (Box 8)
    - Reducing Eye Injuries and Illnesses in Latino Farmworkers Progress Report 2000 (Box 8)
    - Salud Para Todos Implementation Guide 2000 (Box 8)
  - Lay Health Partner Programs
    - "Changes in Empowerment" comments 1996 (Box 8)
    - Community Health Aide Project, Texarkana, AR 1994 (Box 8)
    - Community Health Management Corporation 1993 (Box 8)
    - Final Report 1998 (Box 8)
    - La Familia Sana 1991, undated (Box 8)
    - Lay Health Advisors Curriculum 1987 (Box 8)
    - Maternal and Child Health Migrant Project, North Carolina 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Migrant Farmworker Lay Health Promotion Program (Box 8)
    - National Community Health Advisor Study 1994 (Box 8)
    - Prevention Project 1996 (Box 8)
    - Progress Reports 1992-1997 (Box 8)
    - Teen Programs 1994-1995 (Box 8)
    - Village Health Worker Program, Detroit, MI 1994 (Box 8)
  - REACH Promotora Community Coalition 2003 (Box 8)
- Topical files
  The Topical Files series mostly consists of materials related to federal migrant health issues and information about a major funder of the Migrant Health Promotion, the Catholic Consortium for Migrant Health. Health issues addressed include health care reform, labor camp regulations, and guidance on how to reach migrant workers. This series contains the 1991 Migrant Health Centers Referral Directory. Pages of this volume describe migrant health care centers in Michigan. The materials relating to the Catholic Consortium for Migrant Health include correspondence and meeting minutes and agendas.
  - Annual reports 2002-2008 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Catalyst Newsletter (Box 8)
  - Catholic Consortium for Migrant Health (CCMH)
    - Breakfast meeting 1997, 2000-2001 (Box 8)
    - Conference call minutes and agendas 1986-1996 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Correspondence
      - 1986-1989 (Box 8)
      - 1990-2000 (scattered), 2009 (Box 8)
    - Cover letter template 1988 (Box 8)
    - Grant proposal/invitation to become a member 1991 (Box 8)
    - Meeting minutes and agendas 1984-1998 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Membership and potential members 1986-1998 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Memos 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - Reports from CCMH 1991-1994 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Reports to CCMH from Michigan Health Promotion 1990, 2000 (Box 8)
    - Strategic plans, priorities and overview of responsibilities 1991-1995 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Clippings 1991-2003, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Correspondence to and from government officials 1995-2002 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Farmworker Advisory Council 1991-1999 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Federal Migrant Health Issues
    - Coordination of Migrant and Seasonal Farmworker Service Programs 1993 (Box 8)
    - Environmental Effects on Migrant Health 1989 (Box 8)
    - Federal Funding Guidelines 1988-1989 (Box 9)
    - Federal Migrant Health Program Strategic Work Plan 1988 (Box 9)
    - National Advisory Council on Migrant Health Recommendations 1989 (Box 9)
    - Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Act of 1996 (Box 9)
    - Self-Help Health Promotion 1989 (Box 9)
  - Health Care
    - Health Care Reform 1994 (Box 9)
    - Managed Care and Migrant Workers 1995-1996 (Box 9)
  - Health for the Nation's Harvesters: A History of the Migrant Health Program in its Economic and Social Setting, 1985 (Box 9)
  - HIV/AIDS (Box 9)
  - "Interviews with Migrant Women," 1986 (Box 9)
  - Labor Camp Sanitation Guidelines 1989-1995 (Box 9)
  - Michigan-Texas Organizational development 2004 (Box 9)
  - Midwest Migrant Health Information Office 1993, 1997, undated (Box 9)
  - Migrant Health
    - Children's Health (Box 9)
    - Latinos and HIV 1996, undated (Box 9)
    - Spanish/English Medical Terms 1981 (Box 9)
    - Folk Healing undated (Box 9)